Register of the Russia. Voennyĭ Agent (Japan) Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Russia. Voennyĭ agent (Japan) records,
1906-1921
28013
Russia. Voennyi agent (Japan)
16 manuscript boxes (6.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Letters, telegrams, contracts, minutes, receipts, memoranda, reports, accounts, declarations, requests, orders, instructions, packing and shipping specifications, invoices, insurance policies, bills of lading, blueprints, tables, diagrams, certificates, and lists, relating to the Japanese Army, political movements in Japan, and the purchase by the Russian Army of military supplies from Japanese firms. Also available on microfilm (34 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1928.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (34 reels).
Historical Note
This record group was previously accessioned at the Hoover Institution as the M. P. Podtiagin collection. It consists of the records of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan from 1906 to 1921, plus the files of a number of military offices and organizations subordinate to the Military Attaché. The latter include the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan, the Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration, the Chairman of the Commission for the Inspection of Artillery Supplies Ordered in Japan, the Far Eastern Military Supply Commission, and the Director of Artillery Inspection. These agencies were created to facilitate the purchase and shipment of military supplies from Japan during the period 1914-1921. Upon their dissolution, the records and funds of these agencies were turned over to the Military Attaché.
The office of the Military Attaché in Japan served essentially two purposes. From 1906 to 1914, the Military Attaché sent regular reports to the General Staff Headquarters of the Imperial Russian Army on various characteristics of the Japanese Army (size, organization, troop dispositions, weapons, the military budget, etc.) and on the political situation in Japan. After the outbreak of World War I, the chief duty of the Military Attaché appears to have been the negotiation of contracts with various Japanese firms for the purchase of military supplies (clothing, medical supplies, weapons, raw materials, foodstuffs, etc.), as well as overall direction of inspection and shipment procedures for these goods. The office remained intact after the Russian Revolution in 1917 and continued to serve as a conduit for supplies, first for the Provisional Government, and latter--from 1918 to 1921--for the All-Russian Government at Omsk.
The office of the Military Attaché in Japan was occupied by Major-General V. K. Samoiloff from 1906 to 1915, Colonel N. Morel from 1915 to 1916, Colonel V. Iakhontoff from 1916 to 1918, and Major-General M. P. Podtiagin, the former Senior Tester and Technical Consultant of the Artillery Committee, from 1919 to 1921.
Scope and Content Note
Letters, telegrams, contracts, minutes, receipts, memoranda, reports, accounts, declarations, requests, orders, instructions, packing and shipping specifications, invoices, insurance policies, bills of lading, blueprints, tables, diagrams, certificates, and lists, relating to the Japanese Army, political movements in Japan, and the purchase by the Russian Army of military supplies from Japanese firms.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russia. Armiia--Procurement.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Japan.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Japan.; Japan--Politics and government--20th century.; Japan--Military relations--Russia.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Russia--Military relations--Japan.
Occupations
Military attachés.
Series Description
- Numerical Office File, 1906-1921. (Box 1-16)
  Correspondence, telegrams, reports, receipts, accounts, contracts, insurance policies, bills of lading, debit advice, credit advice, memoranda, diagrams, blueprints, lists, tables, certificates, orders, minutes, information sheets, invoices, signed statements, packing and shipping specifications, acts, agreements, and declarations, arranged in consecutively numbered folders.
Container List
- File Nos. 1-10. Secret reports of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Samoiloff) to General Staff Headquarters, plus related correspondence with the Staff of the Amur Military District, the Staff of the Far Eastern Armies, and the Staff of the Trans-Amur Military District Independent Frontier-Guard Corps, including mimeographed copies of letters, telegram transcripts, reports, authorizations, receipts, tables, and lists, mostly concerning information on the Japanese Army (size, organization, weapons, equipment, troop dispositions, the military budget, etc.) gathered in part from undercover agents and informers. Each folder contains a numerical list of the enclosed correspondence. (Box 1)
  - File No. 1. January-December 1906. (Folder 1: 1)
  - File No. 2. January-October 1907. (Folder 1: 2)
  - File No. 3. October 1907-June 1908. (Folder 1: 3)
  - File No. 4. July 1908-March 1909. (Folder 1: 4)
  - File No. 5. March 1909-December 1909. (Folder 1: 5)
  - File No. 6. January-November 1910. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - File No. 7. December 1910-October 1911. (Folder 2: 2)
  - File No. 8. October 1911-March 1912. (Folder 2: 3)
  - File No. 9. March 1912-October 1912. (Folder 2: 4)
  - File No. 10. October 1912-October 1913. (Box-folder 3: 1)
- File No. 11. Copies of enclosures sent with the reports of the Military Attaché in Japan to General Staff Headquarters, including mimeographed copies of extracts from position papers, instruction sheets, and orders of the Japanese War Department. 1908-1915. (Folder 3: 2)
- File No. 12. Account book of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, listing income and expenditures for sums issued to the account of the Military Attaché in Japan, 1916. (Folder 3: 3)
- File No. 13. Account book of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan,listing expenditures of sums Issued to the account of the Military Attaché in Japan, 1916. (Folder 3: 4)
- File No. 14. Book of credits of the Chief Departments of the War Ministry transferred to the account of the Military Attaché in Japan for payment for military orders, 1916-1917. (Folder 3: 5)
- File No. 15. Book of credits of 1) General Staff Headquarters; 2) Chief Quartermaster's Administration; 3) Chief Ordnance Administration; 4) Chief Military-Technical Administration; and 5) Chief Military Medical Administration, listing income and expenditures for sums transferred by these departments to the account of the Military Attaché in Japan for payment for military supplies purchased by contract with Japanese firms, and also for payment of salaries to staff members commissioned by these departments, 1916-1917. (Folder 3: 6)
- File No. 16. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel lakhontov) and his subordinate, Colonel Podtiagin (Senior Tester and Technical Consultant for the Artillery Committee of the Chief Ordnance Administration) with the Russian Embassy in Tokyo, the Chief of Artillery at the Vladivostok Fortress, and M. Fujii, including letters, contracts, instructions, invoices, certificates, blueprints, diagrams, lists, memoranda, and bills of lading, 1916-1922, concerning the delivery and testing of gun-sighting telescopes for 42-line cannon of the 1905 model according to contract nos. 1372 and 232 with the Fujii Optical Works. (Box-folder 4: 1)
- File No. 17. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Samoiloff) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd. including letters, contracts, bills of lading, signed statements, invoices, insurance policies, and reports, 1915-1916, concerning the inspection and shipment of 600,000 pairs of long boots purchased by the Chief Quartermaster of the Imperial Russian Army at Petrograd from Okura & Co. according to contract no. 90695. (Folder 4: 2)
- File No. 18. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel N. Morel) with the Superintendent for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, contracts, tables, invoices, insurance policies, and reports, 1915-1916, concerning the reception and shipment of 1,000,000 pairs of underwear purchased from Okura & Co. by the District Quartermaster's Administration of the Petrograd Military District (at the front) according to contract no. 96392. (Folder 4: 3)
- File No. 19. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel N. Morel) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, invoices, insurance policies, reports, bills of lading, and tables, 1915-1917, concerning the reception and shipment of 2,700,000 arshins of woolen cloth purchased from Okura & Co. by the Chief Quartermaster's Administration of the Imperial Russian Army according to contract no. 102597. (Folder 4: 4)
- File No. 20. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel N. Morel) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, contracts, invoices, insurance policies, bills of lading, telegrams, and reports, 1916, concerning the reception and shipment of 200,000 pairs of underwear purchased from Okura & Co. by the District Quartermaster's Administration of the Petrograd Military District according to contract no. 9297. (Folder 4: 5)
- File No. 21. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii), the Chosen Hide & Leather Co. (Eitaiho), and the Bank of Chosen, Tokyo Branch, including letters, telegrams, reports, invoices, bills of lading, accounts, declarations, and receipts, 1916-1917, concerning the purchase of 340,000 pairs of military boots from the Chosen Hide & Leather Co. according to contract no. 73 concluded by the Russian Military Attaché in Japan. (Folder 4: 6)
- File No. 22. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel N. Morel) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, contracts, reports, invoices, insurance policies, and bills of lading, 1916, concerning the reception and shipment of 150,000 pairs of boots purchased from Okura & Co. by the District Quartermaster's Administration of the Petrograd Military District according to contract no. 14997. (Box-folder 5: 1)
- File No. 23. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel V. Iakhontoff) with the Bank of Chosen (Tokyo Branch), the Chosen Hide & Leather Co., and the Chief Quartermaster's Administration, including letters, contracts, signed statements, telegrams, bills of lading, and insurance policies, 1916-1919, concerning the shipment and reception of 200,000 ammunition pouches purchased from the Chosen Hide & Leather Co. by the District Quartermaster of the Petrograd Military District according to contract no. 30482. (Folder 5: 2)
- File No. 24. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Iakhontoff) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, contracts, invoices, bills of lading, insurance policies, reports, and telegrams, 1916-1917, concerning the purchase of 2,000,000 leather ammunition pouches from Okura & Co. by the District Quartermaster's Administration of the Petrograd Military District according to contract no. 35947. (Folder 5: 3)
- File No. 25. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Iakhontoff) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii), the Syndicate of Military Boots' Manufacturers in Japan, and the Agent of the Ministry of Trade and Industry at the Russian Embassy in Tokyo (Councillor of State Miller) including letters, contracts, telegrams, information sheets, tables, lists, acts, bills of lading, and reports, 1917-1918, concerning the reception and shipment of 700,000 pairs of military boots by the Russian Government from the Syndicate according to contract no. 536 negotiated by Colonel Iakhontoff. (Folder 5: 4)
- File No. 26. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Samoiloff, Colonel Morel, and Major-General Podtiagin) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii), the Quartermaster's Administration of the Amur Military District, the Quartermaster's Administration of the Petrograd Military District, and the Chief Quartermaster's Administration, including letters, telegrams, reports, certificates, instructions, accounts, receipts, declarations, tables, information sheets, and credit advice, 1915-1921, concerning officials of the Quartermaster's Administration commissioned to work as inspectors in Japan, and the allocation of funds for salaries to these officials. (Box-folder 6: 1)
- File No. 27. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Colonel Samoiloff) with various Japanese firms, including letters,telegrams, estimates, diagrams, blueprints, memoranda, declarations, requests, lists, certificates, reports, and tables, 1914-1917, concerning proposals for the purchase of military supplies (boots, saddles, uniforms, field glasses, searchlights, woolen cloth, canvas, cartridge boxes, various foodstuffs etc.) from these firms. (Folder 6: 2)
- File No. 28. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General V. K. Samoiloff) with the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain F. A. Popovskii), the Russian Volunteer Fleet, the Banque Russo-Asiatique, the Yokahama Specie Bank, Ltd., and various Japanese firms including letters, telegrams, credit advice, bills, debit notes, bills of lading, reports, lists, and tables, 1915-1919, concerning the completion of contracts for military supplies (woolen cloth, uniforms, etc.), inspection of these goods by Russian officials, shipment of the goods to Vladivostok by the Russian Volunteer Fleet, and payment for these services. (Folder 6: 3-4)
- File No. 29. Correspondence of the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General V. K. Samoiloff) with the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain F. A. Popovskii), Mitsui & Co., Ltd., Okura & Co., Ltd., Fukushima & Co., and the Chosen Hide & Leather Co., including letters, telegrams, declarations, reports, bills of lading, insurance policies, requests, invoices, accounts, lists, debit notes, receipts, packing and shipping specifications, and contracts, 1915-1916, concerning proposals for the purchase of military supplies, the completion of orders for military supplies, reception and shipment of these goods, and negotiations concerning reduction in the price of goods rejected by Russian inspectors as being of inferior quality. (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
- File No. 30. Contracts concluded between the District Quartermaster Administration of the Petrograd Military District and Okura & Co., Ltd., and between Mitsui and Co. and the Quartermaster of the 4th Siberian Army Corps, including letters, lists, diagrams and signed statements, 1914-1916. (Folder 7: 3)
- File No. 31. Contracts concluded between the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (acting as agent for the Chief Quartermaster's Administration) and various Japanese firms, including tables, lists, correspondence, and diagrams. 1916-1917. (Folder 7: 4)
- File No. 32. Contracts and agreements concluded between the Special Representative of the Ministry of Supply and Rations (A. V. Tseklinskii) of the Russian Government and various Japanese firms for the purchase of military supplies (boots, shirts, overcoats, etc.), 1919. (Folder 7: 5)
- File No. 33. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Samoiloff), the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, and the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, including letters, reports, accounts, lists, information sheets, declarations, and certificates, 1914-1915, concerning the inspection and shipment of military supplies purchased from Japanese firms, and furnishing information on salaries and expense accounts for official's of the Quartermaster's Department commissioned to work as inspectors in Japan. (Folder 7: 6)
- File No. 34. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, the Director of the Vladivostok Quartermaster's Storage Depot for Imported Goods, and the Chief Quartermaster's Administration, including letters, reports, lists, declarations, information sheets, certificates, and accounts, 1916, concerning the inspection and shipment of military supplies purchased from Japanese firms, the fulfillment of orders for these supplies; and providing information on the activities of Quartermaster's Department officials commissioned to work as inspectors in Japan. (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
- File No. 35. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, the Chief Quartermaster's Administration, and the Director of the Vladivostok Quartermaster's Storage Depot for Imported Goods, including letters, reports, lists, information sheets, receipts, and accounts, 1917, providing information on the fulfillment of orders for military supplies from Japanese firms, and the reception and shipment of these supplies; and detailing expenditures for salaries and expense accounts for Russian inspectors in Japan. (Folder 8: 3)
- File No. 36. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, and the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, including letters, reports, information sheets, lists, memoranda, receipts, telegram transcripts, certificates, and accounts, 1918, providing information on progress in the fulfillment of orders for military supplies from Japanese firms, and on reception and shipment of these supplies; and detailing expenditures for salaries and expense accounts for Russian military inspectors in Japan. (Folder 8: 4)
- File No. 37. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Colonel Popovskii--later Representative of the Supply Department in Japan) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, the Chief Quartermaster, the Special Representative of the Minister of Supply and Provisioning in Japan (N. I. Gerasimov), and the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, including letters, reports, acts, information sheets, certificates, accounts, lists, and telegram transcripts, 1919, providing information on progress in the fulfillment of orders for military supplies from Japanese firms; on the reception, inspection, testing, and shipment of these supplies; on the activities of Russian military inspectors in Japan; and on expenditures for salaries for these officials. (Folder 8: 5-6)
- File No. 38. Correspondence of the Representative of the Supply Department in Japan (Colonel Popovskii) with the Russian Military Attaché in Japan, the Chief Quartermaster, and the Special Representative of the Minister of Supply and Provisioning in Japan, including letters, reports, weekly registers, journal, acts, telegram transcripts, and receipts, 1920, concerning the reception and testing of military supplies purchased from Japanese firms. (Box-folder 9: 1)
- File No. 39. Correspondence of Colonel Popovskii with the Military Attaché in Japan and the Special Representative of the Minister of Supply and Provisioning in Japan, including letters, reports, acts, receipts, accounts, minutes, and information sheets, 1916-1922, providing information on the reception, inspection, and shipment of military supplies purchased from Japanese firms; and relating to staff and office expenses and to the activities of Russian military inspectors in Japan. (Folder 9: 2)
- File No. 40. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, the Military Attaché in Japan (Major-General Samoiloff), and other officials, including letters, telegrams, signed statements, reports, accounts, lists, acts, bills of lading, certificates, declarations, and printed matter, 1914-1916, concerning the duties of and payment to Russian military inspectors in Japan; the conclusion of contracts between the Chief Quartermaster's Administration and various Japanese firms for the purchase of military supplies (boots, ammunition pouches, saddles, etc.); the sending of samples of these goods to the inspectors; and the quality of these goods. (Folder 9: 3)
- File No. 41. Correspondence of the Supervisor for the Inspection of Quartermaster Stores in Japan (Captain Popovskii) with the Military Attaché in Japan, the District Quartermaster of the Amur Military District, the Director of the Vladivostok Quartermaster's Storage Depot for Imported Goods, the Quartermaster of the Vladivostok Fortress, and Okura & Co., Ltd., including letters, telegrams, acts, information sheets, accounts, and reports, 1915-1916, relative to: 1) orders of the Russian Military Attaché, requesting inspection procedures to proceed on military supplies purchased according to certain contracts; 2) shortages or deficiencies in these supplies; 3) staff and office expenses for the military inspectors in Japan. (Folder 9: 4)